<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A seasonable speech, made by a worthy Member of Parliament in the House of Commons, concerning the other House. March 1659.</title>
            <author>Titus, Silius, 1623?-1704.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93023</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2898</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E974_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207825</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866853</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866853</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119141</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93023)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119141)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 145:E974[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A seasonable speech, made by a worthy Member of Parliament in the House of Commons, concerning the other House. March 1659.</title>
                  <author>Titus, Silius, 1623?-1704.</author>
                  <author>Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, Earl of, 1621-1683, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons. preceedings. 1659-03. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Silius Titus. Sometimes also attributed to Anthony Ashley Cooper, Earl of Shaftesbury.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>In this edition line 5 of caption title reads: "in the House of Commons,"; signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "April. 8 1659".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library and the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Identified on UMI microfilm (Early English books, 1641-1700) reel 1770 as Wing (2nd ed.) S2244A.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119141:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SEASONABLE SPEECH, MADE By a worthy Member of PARLIAMENT in the Houſe of Commons, <hi>Concerning the Other Houſe.</hi> March 1659.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. <hi>Speaker,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis daies Debate is but too clear a proof that we Engliſhmen are right Iſlanders, Variable and Mutable like the Air we live in. For (ſir) if that were not our temper, We ſhould not be now Diſputing, Whether after all thoſe hazards we have run, That bloud We have ſpilt, That Treaſure We have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted, we ſhould not now ſit down, juſt where we did begin; and of our own accords ſubmit our ſelves to that Slavery, which we have not only ventured our Eſtates and Lives, but I wiſh I could not ſay, Our Souls and Conſciences, to throw off. What others (ſir) think of this Levity, I cannot tell; I mean thoſe that ſteer their Conſciences by occaſions, and cannot loſe the honour they never had: But truly (ſir) for my own part, I dare as little not declare it to be my Opinion, as others more prudential dare avow it to be theirs, That we are this day making good all the reproaches of our Enemies, owning of our ſelves Oppreſſors, Murderers, Regicides, ſubverters of that, which now we do not only acknowledge to have been a lawful Government, but by recalling it, confeſs it now to be the beſt: Which (ſir) if it be true, and that we now begin to ſee aright, I heartily wiſh, our eyes had been ſooner open; and for three Nations ſake, that we had purchas'd our Conviction at a cheaper rate. We might (ſir) in <hi>Fourty two,</hi> have been, what we thus contend to be in <hi>Fifty nine;</hi> and our Conſciences have had much leſs to anſwer for to God, and our Reputations to the World.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Speaker,</hi> I wiſh with all my ſoul, I did ſtate our Caſe to you amiſs, and that it were the Queſtion only, Whether we would volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily relapſe into the diſeaſe we were formerly poſſeſſed with, and of our own accords take up our old yoke, that we with wearing and cuſtom had made habitual and eaſie, and which (it may be) 'twas more our wantonneſs then our preſſure, that made us throw it off. But this (ſir) is not now the Queſtion: that which we deliberate, is not, Whether we will ſay we do not care to be free, we like our old Maſters, and will now be content to have our ears bored at the door poſts of their houſe, and ſo ſerve them for ever; But (ſir) as if we were contending for ſhame as well as ſervitude, we are carrying our <hi>ears to be bored</hi> at the doors of <hi>an Other Houſe:</hi> A Houſe (ſir) without Name, and therefore it is but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119141:2"/> it ſhould conſiſt of Members without family: A Houſe that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts the Order of Slavery, and ſubjects it to our ſervants; and yet, in contradiction to Scripture, we do not only not think that ſubjection in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable, but are now pleading for it. In a word, ſir, It is a Houſe of ſo incongruous and odious a compoſition and mixture, that certainly the grand Architect would never have ſo framed it, had it not been his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign as well to ſhew to the world <hi>the contempt he had of us,</hi> as to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate <hi>the power he had over us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, That it may appear, that I intend not to be ſo prudent, (as far as my part is concerned) as to make a voluntary Reſignation of my Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Honour to this excellent part of his late Highneſs his laſt Will and Teſtament, I ſhall crave (ſir) the leave to declare in a few particulars my Opinion of this Other Houſe: wherein I cannot but promiſe my ſelf to be favourably heard by ſome, but patiently heard by all: For thoſe Engliſhmen that are againſt this Houſe, will certainly with content hear the Reaſons why others are ſo too; thoſe Courtiers that are for it, give me evidence enough to think that in nature there is nothing which they cannot willingly endure.</p>
            <p>Firſt (ſir) As to the Author and Framer of this Houſe of Peers; Let me put you in minde, it was He, that with reiterated Oaths, had often <hi>ſworn to be true and faithful to the Government without it:</hi> and not only ſworn ſo himſelf, but had been the chief Inſtrument both to draw and compel others to ſwear ſo too. So (ſir) that the foundation of this Noble Fabrick was laid in Perjury, and was begun with the violation and contempt, as well of the Laws of God, as of the Nation. He (ſir) that call'd Monarchy <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> in another, and indeed made it ſo in himſelf: He that voted a Houſe of Lords <hi>dangerous and unneceſſary,</hi> and too truly made it ſo in his partiſans: He that with fraud and force de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived you of your Liberty when he was living, and entailed Slavery upon you at his death: 'tis He (ſir) that hath left you theſe worthy O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeers of that his laſt will and Teſtament; Who, however they have behaved themſelves in other truſts, we may be confident they will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour faithfully to diſcharge themſelves in this. In a word (ſir) had this Other Houſe no other fault but its Inſtitution and Author, I ſhould think that original ſin enough for its condemnation: For <hi>I</hi> am of their opinion that think, that for the good of example, all Acts and Monuments of Tyrants are to be expunged, and eraſed, that if poſſible their memory might be no longer liv'd then their carkaſſes. And the truth is, their good Laws are of the number of their Snares, and but baſe Brokage for our Liberty.</p>
            <p>But Sir, to impute to this Other Houſe no other faults but its own, you may pleaſe in the firſt place to conſider of the power which his Highneſs hath left it, according to that <hi>humble Petition and Advice,</hi> which he was pleaſed to give order to the Parliament to preſent unto him. For (ſir) as the Romans had Kings, ſo had his Highneſs Parliaments amongſt his Inſtruments of ſlavery; And I hope (ſir) it will be no offence for me to pray that his Son may not have them ſo too. But (ſir) they have a <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Voice,</hi> and all other circumſtances of that Arbitrary Power, which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119141:2"/> made the former Houſe intolerable; only the Dignity and Quality of the perſons themſelves is wanting, that our ſlavery may be accompanied with ignominy and affront. And now (Mr. <hi>Speaker</hi>) have we not glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly vindicated the Nations Liberty? have we not worthily imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our Bloud and Treaſure to aboliſh that Power that was ſet over us by the Law, to have the ſame impos'd upon us without a Law? And after all that ſound and noiſe we have made in the World, of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Legiſlative Power, and of the Supremacy and Omnipotency of their Repreſentatives; we now ſee there is no more power left them, but what is put in the balance, and equalled by the power of a few retainers of Tyranny, who are ſo far from being of the Peoples choice, that the moſt part of them are only known to the Nation by the villanies and miſchiefs they have committed in it.</p>
            <p>In the next place (Sir) you may pleaſe to conſider that the perſons inveſted with this power, are all of them nominated and deſigned by the Lord Protector (for to ſay, <hi>by him and his Council,</hi> hath in effect no more diſtinction, then if one ſhould ſay, <hi>by Oliver, and Cromwel.</hi>) By this means the Protector himſelf, by his own and his Peers Negative, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes in effect two of the three Eſtates; and by conſequence, is poſſeſt of two parts of the Legiſlative Power. I think this can be a doubt to no man, that will but take the pains to read over that fair Catalogue of thoſe Noble Lords: for certainly no man that reads their names, can poſſibly fancy for what other vertues or good qualities ſuch a compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition ſhould be made choice of, but only the certainty of their compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with whatſoever ſhould be enjoyned them by their <hi>Creator.</hi> (Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don Sir that name, for 'tis properly appliable, where things are made of nothing.) Now (Sir) if in the former Government, encreaſe of Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was a grievance, becauſe the new Nobility, having freſh obligation to the Crown, were the eaſilier led to compliance with it: And if one of the main Reaſons for excluſion of the Biſhops out of the Houſe of Lords, was becauſe that they being of the Kings making, were in effect ſo many certain Votes for whatever the King had a mind to carry in that Houſe: how much more aſſured will that inconvenience now be, when the Protector, that wants nothing of the King, but, in every ſenſe the Title, ſhall not only make and nominate a part, but of himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute the whole Houſe? In a word (Sir) if our Liberty was endanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the former Houſe, we may give it loſt in the Other Houſe: And 'tis in all reſpects as advantagious and ſecure for the Liberty of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which we come hither to redeem, to allow this power and notion to his Highneſs Officers, or Council, nay his very Chaplains, as to his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures and Partiſans in his Other Houſe.</p>
            <p>Now having conſidered (Sir) their Author, Power, and conſtitution, give me leave to make ſome few Obſervations, though but in general, of the Perſons themſelves that are deſigned to be our Lords and Maſters; and let us ſee what either the extraordinary quality or qualifications are of theſe egregious Legiſlators, which may juſtifie their choice, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with the People to admit them, at leaſt, into equal Authority with the whole Repreſentative Body of themſelves. But what I ſhall ſpeak
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119141:3"/> (Sir) of their quality, or any thing elſe concerning them, I would be thought to ſpeak with diſtinction, and to intend only of the Major part. For I acknowledge, Mr. <hi>Speaker,</hi> the mixture of this Other Houſe to be like the Compoſitions of Apothecaries, who are us'd to mix ſomething of reliſh, ſomething grateful to the Taſte, to qualifie their bitter Drugs, which elſe, perchance, would be immediately ſpit out, and never ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed. So (Sir) His Highneſs, of deplorable memory to this Nation, to countenance as well the want of quality as honeſty in the reſt, hath nominated ſome, againſt whom there lies no other Reproach, but onely that Nomination; but not (Sir) out of any reſpect to their Qualities, or regard to their Vertues, but with regard to the no Quality, to the no Vertues of the reſt: which truly (Mr. <hi>Speaker</hi>) if he had not done, we could eaſily have given a more expreſs Name to his Other Houſe, then he hath been pleaſed to do. For we know a Houſe deſign'd onely for Beggers and Malefactors, is <hi>a Houſe of Correction,</hi> and term'd ſo by your Law. But (Mr. <hi>Speaker</hi>) ſetting thoſe few Perſons aſide, who I hope think the Nomination a diſgrace, and the ever coming to ſit there, much a greater: Can we without Indignation think on the reſt? He that's firſt in their Roll, a condemn'd Coward, one that out of fear and baſeneſs did once what he could to betray your Liberties, and does now the ſame for gain. The ſecond, a Perſon of as little ſence as honeſty, prefer'd for no other reaſon but his no Worth, his no Conſcience; except that his cheating his Father of all he had, was thought a vertue, by him, who by ſad experience, we finde hath done as much for his Mother, his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: The third, a Cavalier, a Presbyterian, an Independent; for a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique, for a Protector, for every thing, for nothing, but onely that one thing, <hi>Mon<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y.</hi> 'Twere endleſs to run through them all, to tell you (Sir) of their Lordſhips of ſeventeen pound Land a year of inheritance; of their Farmer Lordſhips, Dray-men Lordſhips, Cobler Lordſhips, without one foot of Land, but what the bloud of Engliſh-men hath been the price of: theſe (Sir) are to be our Rulers, theſe the Judges of our Lives and Fortunes; to theſe we are to ſtand bare, whilſt their pageant ſtage Lordſhips daign to give us a conference upon their Breeches. Mr. <hi>Speaker,</hi> we have already had too much experience, how unſupportable ſervants are, when they become our Maſters. All kinde of ſlavery is miſerable in the accompt of all generous Mindes; but that which comes accompanied with ſcorn and contempt, ſtirs every Mans Indignation, and is indured by none, whom Nature does not intend for ſlaves, as well as Fortune.</p>
            <p>I ſay not this (Mr. <hi>Speaker</hi>) to revile any man with his meanneſs; for I never thought either the Malignity or Indulgence of Fortune, to be (with wiſe or juſt Men) the grounds either of their ill or their good Opinion. Mr. <hi>Speaker,</hi> I blame not in theſe Men the faults of their Fortune, any otherwiſe but as they make them their own: I object to you their Poverty, becauſe it is accompanied with Ambition; I minde you of their Quality, becauſe they themſelves forget it. So that 'tis not the Men I am angry with, but with their Lordſhips; not with Mr. <hi>Barkſtead,</hi> or Mr. <hi>Goaler</hi> (Titles I could well allow him) but with <hi>The
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119141:3"/> Right Honourable, our ſingular good Lord and Goaler:</hi> 'Tis this incongru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity (Mr. <hi>Speaker</hi>) I am diſpleaſed with.</p>
            <p>So (Sir) that though we eaſily grant Poverty and Neceſſity to be no faults, yet we muſt allow them to be great Impediments in the way of Honour, and ſuch as nothing but extraordinary Vertue and Merit can well remove. The Scripture reckons it among <hi>Jeroboams</hi> great faults, that <hi>he made prieſts of the meaneſt of the p ople;</hi> and ſure it was none of the Vertues of our <hi>Jeroboam</hi> (who hath ſet up his Calves too, and would have our Tribes come up and worſhip them) that he obſerved the ſame Method, in making of Lords.</p>
            <p>One of the few Requeſts the Portugals made to <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond of <hi>Spain,</hi> when he got that Kingdom (as His late Highneſs did this) by an Army, was, <hi>That he would not make Nobility contemptible, by advancing ſuch to that Degree, whoſe quality or vertue could be no way thought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it.</hi> Nor have we formerly been leſs apprehenſive of ſuch inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies our ſelves: it was in <hi>Ric.</hi> 1's time, one of the Biſhop of <hi>Ely</hi>'s Accuſations, that Caſtles and Forts of truſt he did <hi>Obſcuriis &amp; ignotis hominibus tradere,</hi> put in the hands of obſcure and unknown Men: But We (Mr. <hi>Speaker</hi>) to ſuch a kind of Men are delivering up the Power of our Laws, and in that the power of All.</p>
            <p>In the 17 <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. there paſt an Act of Parliament, for the degrading of <hi>John Nevil</hi> Marqueſs <hi>Mountague</hi> and Duke of <hi>Bedford;</hi> the reaſon expreſt in the Act, <hi>Becauſe he had not a Revenue ſufficient for the maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that Dignity;</hi> to which he added,, <hi>That when men of mean birth are called to high Eſtate, and have no livelihood to ſupport it, it induceth Bribe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Extortions, and all kinds of injuſtices that are followed by gain.</hi> And in the Parliament of 2 <hi>Carol.</hi> the Peers in a Petition againſt Scotiſh and Iriſh Titles, told the King, <hi>That 'tis a Novelty without Preſident, That Men ſhould poſſeſs Honours, where they poſſeſs nothing elſe; and that they ſhould have a Vote in Parliament, where they have not a foot of land.</hi> But if it had been added, Sir, <hi>Or have no Land but what is the purchaſe of their Villanies,</hi> againſt how many of our new Peers had this been an impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Objection? To conclude (Sir) It hath been a very juſt and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable care, amongſt all Nations, not to render that deſpis'd and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible to the People, which is deſign'd for their Reverence, and their Awe: Which (Sir) bare and empty Title, without quality or vertue, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver procured any man, any more then the Image in the Fable made the Aſs adored that carried it.</p>
            <p>After their quality, give me leave (Sir) to ſpeak a word or two of their qualifications; which certainly ought in reaſon to carry ſome propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the employments they deſign themſelves. The Houſe of Lords (Sir) are our Kings Hereditary great Councils: they are the Higheſt Court of Judicature; they have their part in Judging and Determining of the Reaſons of making new Laws, and of abrogating old: From a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them we take our great Officers of State; they are commonly our Generals at Land, and our Admirals at Sea: In concluſion (Sir) they are both of the Eſſence and Conſtitution of our old Government; and have beſides, the greateſt and nobleſt ſhare in the Adminiſtration.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119141:4"/> Now certainly (Sir) to judge according to the Dictates of Reaſon, one would imagine ſome ſmall Faculties and Endowments to be neceſſary for the diſcharging of ſuch a Calling; and thoſe ſuch as are not uſually acquired in ſhops and ware-houſes, nor found by following the Plough: Now what other Academies moſt of their Lordſhips have been bred in, but their Shops; what other Arts they have been verſed in, but thoſe which more require good Arms and good Shoulders, then good Heads, I think (Mr. <hi>Speaker</hi>) we are yet to be informed. Sir, we commit not the Education of our Children to Ignorant and Illiterate Maſters; Nay, we truſt not our very Horſes to unskilful Grooms: I beſeech you (Sir) let Us think it belongs to Us, to have ſome Care into whoſe Hands we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the management of the Commonwealth: And if we cannot have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Birth and Fortune to be our Rulers, to whoſe quality we would willingly ſubmit; I beſeech you (Sir) for our Credits and Safeties ſake, let us ſeek men (at leaſt) of Parts and Education, to whoſe Abilities we may have ſome reaſon to give way. If, Sir, a Patient dies under a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians hand, the Law eſteems that not a Felony, but a misfortune in the Phyſician; but if one that is no Phyſician undertakes the management of a Cure, and the Party miſcarries; the Law makes the Emperique a Felon, and ſure in all Mens opinion the Patient a Fool. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude (Sir) for Great Men to govern 'tis ordinary: for Able Men 'tis natural; Knaves many times come to it by Force and Neceſſity, and Fools ſometimes by Chance: But univerſal Choice and Election of Fools and Knaves for Government, was never yet made by any who were not themſelves like thoſe they choſe.</p>
            <p>But me thinks (Mr. <hi>Speaker</hi>) I ſee ready to riſe after me, ſome Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman that ſhall tell you the great ſervices that their new Lordſhips have done the Commonwealth; that ſhall extol their Valour, their God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, their Fidelity to the Cauſe; The Scripture too (no doubt) as 'tis to all purpoſes, ſhall be brought in to argue for them; and we ſhall hear of the <hi>Wiſdom of the poor man that ſaved the City,</hi> of the <hi>not many wiſe, not many mighty;</hi> Atributes I can no way deny to be due to their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips. Mr. <hi>Speaker,</hi> I ſhall be as forward as any man to declare their ſervices, and acknowledge them; though I might tell you, that the ſame honour is not purchas'd by the bloud of an Enemy, and of a Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen; that for Victories in civil Wars, till our Armies march through the City, I have not read that the Conquerours have been ſo void of ſhame as to Triumph. <hi>Caeſar,</hi> not much more indulgent to his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, then our late Protector, did not ſo much as write publique Letters of his Victory at <hi>Pharſalia,</hi> much leſs had daies of Thankſgiving to his gods, and Anniverſary feaſts for having been a proſperous Rebel, and given Juſtice and his Country the worſt.</p>
            <p>But Sir, I leave this Argument, and to be as good as my word, come to put you in mind of ſome of their ſervices, and the obligation you owe them for the ſame. To ſpeak nothing (Sir) of one of my Lords Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners valour at <hi>Bristol,</hi> nor of another Noble Lords brave adventure at the Bear-Garden; I muſt tell you Sir, that moſt of them have had the courage to do things, which (I may boldly ſay) few other Chriſtians
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119141:4"/> durſt have ſo adventured their ſouls to have attempted: They have not only ſubdued their Enemies, but their Maſters, that raiſed and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained them; they have not only Conquered <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> but Rebellious <hi>England</hi> too; and there ſuppreſt a Malignant Party of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and Laws. And that nothing ſhould be wanting to make them indeed compleat Conquerours, (without the help of Philoſophy) they have even Conquered themſelves. All ſhame they have ſubdued, as perfectly as all Juſtice; the Oathes they have taken, they have as ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily digeſted, as their old General could himſelf; Publique Covenants and Engagements, they have trampled under foot: In concluſion, ſo intire a Victory they have over themſelves, that their Conſciences are as much their ſervants, as (Mr. <hi>Speaker</hi>) we are. But (ſir) give me leave to conclude with that which is more admirable then all this, and ſhews the confidence they have of themſelves and us: After having many times trampled on the Authority of the Houſe of Commons, and no leſſe then five times diſſolv'd them, They hope for thoſe good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices to the Houſe of Commons, by the Houſe of Commons to be made a Houſe of Lords.</p>
            <p>I have been over-long (ſir) for which I crave your pardon; therefore in a word I conclude. I beſeech you let us think it our duty to have a care of two things: Firſt, That Villanies be not encouraged with the rewards of Virtue: Secondly, That the Authority and Majeſty of the Government of this Nation be not defiled, and expoſed to contempt, by committing ſo conſiderable a part of it to Perſons of as mean Quality as Parts.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Thebans</hi> did not admit Merchants into Government, till they had left their traffick ten years: ſure 'twould have been long before Coblers and Dray-men would have been allowed. If (ſir) the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of this Houſe ſhall finde it neceſſary to begin where we left, and ſhall think we have been hitherto like the Prodigal, and that now when our neceſſities perſwade us <hi>(i. e.)</hi> that we are almoſt brought to herd it with Swine, now 'tis high time to think of a return; Let us without more ado, without this motley mixture, even take our <hi>Rulers as at the firſt,</hi> ſo that we can be but reaſonably ſecured to avoid our <hi>Counſellours as at the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Give me leave (ſir) to releaſe your Patience with a ſhort ſtory. <hi>Livy</hi> tells us, There was a State in <hi>Italy,</hi> an Ariſtocracy, where the Nobility ſtretcht their Prerogative too high, and preſumed a little too much upon the Peoples Liberty and Patience; whereupon the diſcontents were ſo general and ſo great, that they apparently tended to a diſſolution of Government, and the turning of all things into Anarchy and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. At the ſame time, beſides theſe diſtempers at home, there was a potent Enemy ready to fall upon them from abroad, that had been an over-match for them at their beſt Union, but now in theſe diſorders, was like to finde them very ready and very eaſie prey: A wiſe man (ſir) in the City, that did not at all approve of the inſolency of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, and as a little liked Popular tumults, bethought himſelf of this Stratagem, to couzen his Countrey into ſafety. Upon a pretence of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119141:5"/> Counſel, he procured the Nobility to meet all together; which when they had done, he found a way to lock all the doors upon them; goes away himſelf, and takes the keys with him: Then immediately he ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons the People; tells them, that by a contrivance of his, he had taken all the Nobility in a Trap; That now was the time for them to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged upon them for all their inſolencies; That therefore they ſhould immediately go along with him and diſpatch them. Sir, the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of our Army after a faſt, could not be more ready for the villany, then this People were; And accordingly they made as much haſte to the ſlaughter as their Lord Protector could deſire them. But Sir, this wiſe man I told you of, was their Lord Protector indeed: As ſoon as he had brought the People where the Parliament was ſitting, and when they but expected the word to fall to the Butchery, and take their heads; <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> ſaies he, <hi>Though I would not care how ſoon this work of Reformation were over; yet in this Ship of the Commonwealth we muſt not throw the Steers-men over board, till we have provided others for the Helm: Let us conſider before we take theſe men away, in what other hands we may more ſecurely truſt our Liberty, and the management of the Commonwealth.</hi> And ſo he advis'd them before the putting down of the former, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think themſelves of conſtituting an Other Houſe: He begins and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates one, a man highly cryed up in the Popular faction, a confiding man, one of much zeal, little ſenſe, and no quality; you may ſuppoſe him (ſir) a zealous Cobler: the People in concluſion murmured at this, and were loath their fellow-Mutineer, for no other virtue but Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tining, ſhould come to be advanced to be their Maſter; and by their looks and murmur, ſufficiently expreſt the diſtaſte they took at ſuch a motion. Then he nominates another, as mean a mechanique as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; you may imagine him, Sir, a buſtling rude Dray-man, or the like: He was no ſooner named, but ſome burſt out a laughing, others grew angry and railed at him, and all deteſted and ſcorn'd him. Upon this a third was named for a Lordſhip, one of the ſame batch, and every way fit to ſit with the other two. The People then fell into a confuſed laugh and noiſe, and enquired, if ſuch were Lords, who (by all the Gods) would be content to be the Commons?</p>
            <p>Sir, Let me be bold (by the good leave of the Other Houſe and yours) to ask the ſame Queſtion? But Sir, to conclude this ſtory, and with it I hope the Other Houſe: when this wiſe man I told you of, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived they were now ſenſible of the inconvenience and miſchief they were running into, and ſaw that the pulling down their Rulers, would prove in the end, but the ſetting up of their ſervants; He thought them then prepar'd to hear Reaſon; and told them, <hi>You ſee,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>That as bad as this Government is, we cannot, for any thing I ſee, agree upon a better: What then, if after this fright we have put our Nobility in, and the demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration we have given them of our power, we try them once more, whether they will mend, and for the future behave themſelves with more moderation?</hi> That people (M. <hi>Speaker</hi>) were ſo wiſe as to comply with that wiſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and to think it eaſier to mend their old Rulers, then to make New. And I wiſh (Mr. <hi>Speaker</hi>) we may be ſo wiſe to think ſo too.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:119141:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
